这个实验对比锁实验。
The lab compares to the locking lab.
它更直截一点。
It was a bit more straightforward.
好的，你完成了吗，
Good, are you completely,
你完成实验了吗，还是。
have you finished the lab, or you are.
我昨天刚开始，一半了，所以。
I just started yesterday and a halfway, so.
好的，我想这对刚开始的人来说是个好消息，
Okay, good, I guess that's good news for people who are starting,
有人完成了吗？
anybody finished it yet?
我完成了。
I have, I finished it.
有令人不快的意外或者得到很好的解决？
And any any nasty surprises or worked out reasonably well?
我想它成功了，是的。
I think it worked out okay, yeah.
比锁实验容易多了？
Much easier than the lock lab?
至少我是这么认为的。
I think so, at least.
好的，希望其他人也是如此。
Well, hopefully will be the case for everybody else too.
好的，让我开始吧，
Yeah yeah, let me get started
我今天要讨论的话题是用户应用程序的虚拟内存，
and the topic I want to talk about today is virtual memory for user applications,
在 1991 年这篇由 Appel 和 Li 编写的论文的指导下。
you know on sort of guided by this paper from 1991, by Appel and Li.
所以我们的出发点是，
So the starting point basically is that,
如你们所知，
as you well know,
操作系统内核以创造性的方式使用虚拟内存页表。
that the OS kernel use virtual memory page tables in creative ways.
你已经看到我们有一个懒分配实验，写时复制实验，
You've seen that we have a lazy allocation lab, copy-on-write lab,
以及许多其他类型的特性，
as well as many other sort of features,
在 xv6 中实现的各个方面，
that you know implementation to or aspects of the implementation in the xv6, so.
这篇论文的论点，
And basically the argument that the paper makes, the paper argues,
用户应用程序应该受益于
you know the user application should actually benefit to
或应该具有相同的能力，
or should have the same powers,
用户应用程序也可以使用虚拟内存。
you know, user apps can use VM too.
我的意思是，
A little bit, I mean when I mean again,
当然，你的应用程序使用虚拟内存，
of course, your application running with virtual memory,
但我对 VM 真正的意思是，
but I really mean with VM is that
它们希望有与内核相同的机制，
they would like to have the same mechanisms that kernel has
在用户模式访问用户应用程序，
to its access user application where in user mode,
应用程序能够接受页面错误，
application will be able to take page faults,
然后可以响应这些页面错误，
and then you know respond to those page faults,
可以修改保护位，
you know be able to change the protection bits,
或修改页表中的特权级别。
or the privilege level to levels in the page table.
所以，在这篇论文中讨论这种情况，
And so, in the paper argues this case
通过观察一系列不同的应用程序，
by looking at a bunch of different applications,
比如六、七种不同类型的应用程序，
like six or seven different types of applications
也许我会问你，什么是你最喜欢的应用程序，
and maybe I will ask you like what was your favorite application,
你在论文中遇到的。
you encountered in the paper.
有没有人想说一下？
Anybody wanna [chime] in and talk the?
它们可以允许用户应用程序决定，
They can allow the user application to decide that
一个页面可以，
a page is going to be,
我猜他们更改了某个特定页面的访问位。
I guess they change the access bits for some particular page.
是的，这是其中一种机制，
Yeah, that's one of the mechanisms,
我只是好奇有哪些应用程序，
I'm just curious which applications,
你知道，他们用很多不同的应用程序来证明这一点，
you know they make the case with a bunch of different applications,
比如垃圾收集器或并发垃圾收集器，
like the garbage collector or concurrent garbage collector,
还有其他几个，
and a couple other ones,
只是想知道你觉得哪几个最有趣。
you know just wondering which ones you thought were most interesting.
他们还使用哪些其他应用程序来证明自己的观点。
What other applications do they use or the used to make their case.
我认为数据压缩应用程序非常酷。
I thought the data compression application was pretty cool.
另一种[]是，
And the other [] were,
人们[]。
people were [] by.
我认为在多个不同系统之间共享虚拟内存非常酷，
I thought the sort of shared virtual memory between multiple different systems that was pretty cool,
我想我没有完全理解它是怎么运作的，
I didn't, I don't think I fully understood how it worked,
但是使用保护位的总体思路是
but the general idea of using the protection bits
确保不同机器以正确方式使用共享内存，
to make sure that different machines are are using that shared memory in the right way
保护不变量是有意义的。
and protecting invariance makes sense.
所以，就是这样，
So, that's it,
基本上整个领域发展使用这种方法，
you know basically it turns out that whole area developed in way that one,
论文最初描述的支持向量机，
paper originally described the SVM,
发展一个完整的研究领域，
developing a whole research area,
人们用各种聪明的技巧
where you know people all kinds of clever tricks
试着实现这种方案。
to try to make that actually that scheme to fly.
还有其他的吗？
Any others?
因为他们会去做一些其他的应用程序，
Because they go off and do a couple other paper applications
他们基本上认为，
and they basically argue that
如果你观察所有这些完全不同的应用程序，
you know if you look at all these different quite different applications
比如共享虚拟内存，数据压缩或垃圾收集器，
like shared virtual memory data compression or garbage collector,
本质上有很大的不同，
you know very different in nature,
但事实证明，
but it turns out that,
它们都依赖于
all of them actually rely on
少量的虚拟内存原语使其真正工作。
a small number of virtual memory primitives to actually make it work.
所以论文[]的第一个问题是，
And so the first question to the paper [] is
比如，需要的原语应该是什么样子，
like okay what what what should the primitives look,
比如用户应用程序需要的，
like the user application needs,
如果它们想要实现其中一个应用程序。
if they want to implement one of those applications.
所以让我稍微讨论一下这个，
And so let me talk a little bit about that,
首先，什么是原语。
first you know what primitives is.
所以它们是，
And so they are,
它们是显而易见的，
the ones they the obvious one,
当然你需要一些原语，
of course you need something of a primitive,
让我们看 Trap ，
let's go what I call Trap,
允许内核内部发生的页面错误，
basically to allow a page fault that happens sort of inside the kernel
传播到用户空间。
to be propagated up to user space.
然后在用户空间中，
And then in user space,
处理程序可以处理它的页面错误，
you know the handler can then deal with its page fault
然后以通常的方式返回内核，
and then of course return in the usual way back to the kernel,
然后恢复指令。
and then resume the instruction.
所以很明显这样的原语是必要的，
So clearly the primitive like that is necessary,
否则你无法对页面错误做出任何响应。
because otherwise you couldn't do anything in response to a page fault.
另一个要讨论的原语是 Prot1 ，
The other primitive you know they talk about this Prot1,
这降低了页面的可访问性，
which decreases the accessibility of page,
他们谈论了很多关于可访问性的问题，
they talk a lot about accessibility,
或者你知道可访问性是什么意思？
or and what do you mean with accessibility?
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
是否可读写。
Whether is read, write.
是的，有不同的方式
Yeah, yeah, so there's different ways
来降低它们的可访问性，
in which you can decrease their accessibility,
你从一个页面读写到只读，
you go from a page that maybe has read write go to just read only,
或者你从只读到根本没有访问权限。
or maybe you go from read only to actually have no access at all.
他们还提出，
They also proposed that,
每个页面都应该有一个 Prot1 ，
basically there should be one for each individual page, that's Prot1,
也应该有一个，
there should be one
你可以对应用程序的页面集合进行调用，
that actually you can do for the application call for a collection of pages,
所以 ProtN 原则上归结为
and so basically ProtN boils down in principle
调用 Prot1 N 次，
to calling Prot1 N times,
但是，他们讨论为什么，
but why, why do they argue that
我们也应该有这个 ProtN 原语。
we should have actually a ProtN version of this primitive too.
是不是因为它更有效率，
Is it because actually it's more efficient,
因为保护 N 个页面的开销
because the overhead of protecting the N pages
并不比保护一个页面多多少，
is not much more than protecting one,
因为，他们谈到了一些比如摊销的东西。
because, they talked about something like amortizing the work of.
是的，完全正确，
Yeah yeah, absolutely right,
所以如果你做一个 Prot1 ，
so basically if you do a Prot1,
你必须更改页表位，并做一些工作，
basically you have to change the page table bits, and do some work,
然后在 Prot1 的后面，
and then at the end of that Prot1,
通常需要刷新 TLB ，
you know typically want to have to flush the TLB,
这是在 xv6 中实现的，
remember this from xv6 implementation,
而刷新 TLB 很昂贵，
and flushing TLB is expensive
如果能摊销，那就更好了，
and it would be nice if you could amortize
在整个页表变化时，刷新 TLB 。
basically flushing TLB overall you know the page table changes.
所以， ProtN 可以归结为 N 次，
So basically ProtN boils down to N times
N 次更改页表位加上一次 TLB 刷新。
N times changing page table bits plus one TLB flush.
如果你做 N 次 Prot1 ，
And if you did N times Prot1,
你将有一个页表切换，
you would have a one page table switch
加上一个页表修改，
plus one page table modification
以及每页的一个 TLB 刷新，
plus one TLB flush from each page,
这样你可以节省 TLB 刷新。
so you can save the TLB flush.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，然后原语的 Unprot ，
Okay, then you know the primitive Unprot,
这增加了可访问性，
this increases accessibility as they call it,
基本上就是说，
basically meaning you know,
比如，如果页面现在有只读访问，
if page for example have what had read only access now,
我们将其提升为具有读写访问权限。
we're just going to promote it to actually have read and write access.
这里还提到了另外两个原语，
There are two other primitives are mentioning,
一个原语是找出脏页面，
one is primitive to actually find out which page which page is dirty,
以及另一个原语 Map2 ，
and another primitive Map2,
允许一个应用程序
which allows, to allows an application
在同一个地址空间映射两次，
to map a particular range twice in the same address page,
同一个地址空间，
the same address space,
但具有不同程度的可访问性。
but with a different degrees of accessibility.
我们一会儿就能看到这一点。
We'll see that showing up in a second.
所以你看看这些原语，
So you look at these primitives,
xv6 支持其中的任何一个，
you know xv6 support any of these,
对于用户级应用程序。
you know for user level applications.
不是开箱即用，
Not out of the box,
但是也许我们实现的警报处理程序感觉很接近。
but maybe the alarm handler that we implemented feels close.
好的，他们把警报处理程序记在脑海里，
Good yeah, they keep the alarm handler in their mind,
当然与 Trap 的感觉非常接近，
that certainly feels very close correctly that is related to the Trap one,
但除此之外，
but other than that,
xv6 不支持任何一个，
there are xv6 support none of this, right,
实际上它是一个非常小的 Unix 接口，
actually it's a very minimal Unix interface,
不支持任何更高级的虚拟内存原语，
doesn't support any of the more advanced virtual memory primitives,
即使在内部内核本身确实具有所有可用的机制，
even though internally the kernel itself does have all the mechanism available,
但是你不会将系统调用暴露到用户空间。
but you're not exposed to user space into a form of system calls.
所以，论文认为，
As a result, the papers arguing that
任何一种好的操作系统都应该提供
any sort of good operating systems should provide
这些原语或系统调用，
you know these primitives or system calls,
以便应用程序可以使用它们。
so the application can use them.
所以自然与这个问题有关，
So that naturally relates to the question,
比如，我们今天的 Unix 有多大的范围可用，
like what what's the scope you know we've Unix today are available,
事实证明，任何，
it turns out, basically you know any,
看看现代的 Unix ，比如 Linux ，
look at modern Unix like Linux,
你知道这些原语就在那里，
you know these primitives are there,
也许与论文中讨论的不完全一样，
maybe not exactly the same flavor as argued in the paper,
但它们确实存在。
but they are there.
你甚至在论文中看到了，
You even saw it in the paper, correct
或者某些操作系统确实具有它们子集的某个版本，
or some of the operating system did have some version of a subset of them,
但今天它们基本上广泛支持。
but today they basically widely supported.
如果你看看今天的 Unix ，
If you look at Unix today,
让我们看看它是如何实现它的。
let's see how it actually there instantiate it.
所以第一个，
And so one of the first ones
可能是最重要的一个，
is probably the most important one
就是所谓的 mmap ，
is something that's just called mmap,
它可以用来获取某个对象，
and that can be used to take some object
并将其映射到调用者的地址空间中，
and map it into the address space of the caller,
比如你想要映射一个文件，
sort of example if you want to map a file,
然后系统调用有以下的形式，
you know, then you know the system calls something of the following form,
调用 mmap ，
you know call mmap,
mmap 有相当多的参数，
mmap actually has quite a bit of a building number of arguments,
第一个是，
the first basically says like what you,
你可以指定一个想要映射的地址，
you can specify a particular address you would like it to be mapped to
或者你可以让内核决定选择地址，
or you can let the kernel decides to choose the address,
在这种情况下，你指定 null ，
and in that case, you specified just null
然后内核选择对象要映射的地址，
and kernel pick an address where to map you know the object,
指定长度，
specify the length,
指定保护位，
you specify the protection bits,
比如读/写，
you know, for example read slash write,
然后一些我们要讨论的参数，
and then you know some argument, we want to talk about,
还有一个叫做 MAP_PRIVATE 的东西，
and there's something called MAP_PRIVATE,
你必须说一些事情，
basically you have to say something about how,
如果写那个特定的对象，会发生什么，
what happens if you actually write to that particular object,
我们跳过大多数，
let's skip that mostly,
然后你可以，
then you can for,
我们可以传入文件描述符和偏移量，
we can actually pass in the file descriptor and offset,
这就是说，
and basically what this says is that
你应该映射文件对象的内容，
you know you should map the content of the file object,
由文件描述符指向，
pointed to by the file descriptor
然后你从偏移量获取对象的文件内容，
and you take the file content to the object you know at offset,
使用长度映射那个特定地址。
map that basically that particular particular address you know with that length.
所以，这允许你提供
And so this basically allows you to serve
所谓的内存映射文件，
what is called memory map file,
你可以将文件内容放入你的地址空间，
so you can bring the contents of the file into your address space,
实际上调用读取或写入系统调用。
would actually having to call read or write system calls.
这在某种程度上是很方便的，
It's sort of convenient, correct,
因为这样你可以只用普通的指针来操作文件，
because then you can manipulate the file just ordinary pointers,
你可以在特定位置写入，
you can write at particular locations
然后在某个点上，你可以写回到磁盘，
and then at some point you can write to come back to to the disk
所以它是操作数据结构的方便的接口，
and so it is a convenient interface to a manipulate data structures,
可能存储在文件中。
that might be stored into might be stored in the file.
实际上，你将实现这个特定版本的 mmap ，
And in fact, you will be implementing this specific version of mmap
或者基于文件的 mmap 的某个版本，
or some version of the file based mmap
在下一个实验中。
actually in the next lab.
这集成了 xv6 的文件系统部分，
So this basically integrates you know the file system part of xv6,
xv6 的虚拟内存部分，
you know virtual memory part of xv6
你可以将它们联系起来，
and you can sort of hook them up
通过实现 mmap ，
and by supplying by actually implementing mmap,
mmap 还可以以其他方式使用，
mmap can also be used in other ways,
你可以使用映射文件，
so you can use the map file,
你也可以用它来映射匿名内存，
you can also use it to map anonymous memory,
这是对 sbrk 的一种替代，
and that's basically sort of an alternative to sbrk
你可以要求内核，
where you can sort of ask the kernel,
请给我一些内存，
please you know give me a bunch of memory,
并且映射在这个特定的地址。
and you know map at this particular address.
所以这是核心系统调用之一，
So that is one of the core system calls
并与第二个原语[相关]。
and [related] back to the primitives in the second.
好的，还有几个调用是必要的，
Okay, there's a couple more calls that are necessary
以支持论文所主张的原语，
to actually support the primitives at the paper argued for
Unix 拥有它们，
and Unix has has them,
所以更多的关于今天的 Unix，
so there's more Unix today,
这里有一个 mprotect 系统调用，
there's an mprotect system call,
一旦你将某些内容映射到地址空间，
so once you have something mapped into the address space,
你可以更改权限，
you can actually you know change the the permissions,
所以无论什么，
so whatever you can make
mprotect 映射某些东西到地址空间，
it just you know mprotect the particular map something into the address space,
然后 mprotect ，比如它的一部分或全部的子集，
then you know mprotect for example for a subset of that part or all of it
并将其映射到特定的保护级别，
and map it to particular protection level,
比如，如果你做了这个，
so for example if you did this,
可以执行加载，
basically loads could be executed,
但是保存会变成一个页面错误，
but stores would you know change into change into a page fault
同样，如果你想确保
and similarly if you want to make sure
地址空间中的范围完全不可访问，
that range in address space is completely inaccessible,
你可以，对 mprotect 使用 NONE ，
then you can, mprotect with NONE
然后它们，
and you know basically then both,
任何对这个页面或这个地址范围的访问，
everything basically, every access to that particular page or to that address range
从地址到地址加上长度，
starting from address to address plus length,
将导致页面错误。
will result in a page fault.
还有一个类似的版本，
There's a similar version,
对 mmap 有一个相应的调用，叫做 unmap ，
there's a corresponding call to mmap called unmap,
这允许你删除映射或删除地址范围。
that allows you to basically remove a mapping or remove an address range.
如果你好奇这些调用是怎么工作的，
And actually, if you curious you know exactly how these calls work,
你可以查看这些系统调用的手册页。
you know you should look up the man page of these system calls.
最后，我们真正需要的是系统调用 sigaction ，
And then finally you know the one that we really need is system call sigaction,
这是一个信号处理程序，
and basically this is a signal handler,
并允许应用程序，
and allows the application
比如，如果某个特定信号发生，
to say like you know if a particular signal happens,
然后调用这个特殊的函数，
then you know call this particular function,
所以也许你可以安装函数 f
so maybe you can install basically function f
作为特定信号的信号处理程序，
as a signal handler for a particular signal,
在页面错误的情况下，
and in the case of you know page faults,
产生的信号叫做 segfault ，
you know the signal that is generated yeah something was called segfault,
你可能以前在用户代码中看到过 segfault ，
typically, you might have seen segfault in user code before,
通常在 segfault 中发生的情况是
you know typically what happens in the segfault is
应用程序停止和崩溃，
basically application stops and crashes,
但是如果应用程序安装了处理程序，
but if the application had installed a handler
对于 segfault 事件或 segfault 信号，
for you know segfault event or segfault signal,
那么不是停止应用程序，
then instead of the application being stopped,
而是处理程序被内核调用，
the handler would have been called by the kernel,
然后应用程序可能会响应该特定的 segfault ，
and then the application can maybe respond to that particular segfault,
以内核响应页面错误的同样的方式，
in the same way in some sense that the kernel responds to a page fault
可能还会修复页表，
and maybe fixes up the page table,
这样可以继续执行，
so that you know the execution can continue
在这种情况下，也许处理程序会调用 mprotect ，
and in this case, maybe the handler will actually call mprotect
或修改权限，
or change the permissions,
这样指令就可以恢复并继续。
so that actually the instruction can resumed and continue.
在这件事上，
And, so in this in fact,
我们最熟悉的版本，
you know you are the most familiar version that we were,
我们所看到的 sigaction ，比如 sigalarm ，
the things that we've seen like a sigaction much like sigalarm,
就像 Amir 之前提到的，
as Amir mentioned a little bit earlier,
在 sigalarm 实验中，
in this sigalarm lab,
你可以安装 alarm 程序，
where you could install the alarm program,
安装一个处理程序，
basically installed a handler,
它在每个时钟周期调用，
that will have to be called at every clock tick
或每个时间段调用，
or every you know period of time,
基本上， sigaction 在某种程度上等同于，
and you know basically sigaction is sort of the equivalent that,
可以对不同类型的信号做出反应。
the general version of it where basically can respond to different types of signals.
关于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
这里像是 mprotect 实现了，
It seems like mprotect implies that
你可以在各个地址上添加不同的权限级别，
you can add different permission levels on individual addresses
而在我们一直在使用的 xv6 中，
whereas in like xv6 that we've been working with,
你只能在整页上应用权限，
you can only apply permissions on full pages,
那是不同的， mprotect 。
is that is that a difference, that's mprotect.
不，这不是真正的不同，
No, it's not real difference,
它是在页面级别的粒度上工作的，
you know it works at a page level granularity,
而且它不会暴露，
and it doesn't expose,
有一个单独的调用来找出页面的大小，
you know there's a separate call to find out what the page page sizes,
如果你好奇的话。
if you actually curious about it.
谢谢。
Thank you.
所以如果你想一想论文中的原语，
Um, so if you think about the primitives that were in the paper,
我们可以把它们映射起来，
you know we can map them correctly,
比如现代 Unix 或Unix 通常提供的。
like what currently Unix or Unix typically provide.
那么， Trap 对应的是什么，
So, what equivalent correct to Trap,
在 Unix 中会提供的
you know that we're in Unix would be provided
就是 sigaction 调用。
something called the sigaction sigaction call.
关于 ProtN 和 Prot1 ，
And about you know ProtN and Prot1,
它们相当于什么？
what is the equivalent to that?
好的，这三个都可以使用 mprotect 来实现，
Okay, so basically all three of them correctly can be implemented using mprotect,
而且 mprotect 非常灵活，
and mprotect you know is flexible enough,
你可以在一页上使用它，
that you could do it by a single page
或者你可以提供由多个页面组成的内容，
or actually just ask or you can actually provide something consists of multiple pages
然后你可以得到刷新一次 TLB 的好处，
and then you could do, you get the same benefit of one TLB flush,
用于更改一系列页面上的权限。
for changing permissions on a whole series of pages.
好吧？
Okay?
这些调用可以直接映射到一些原语中，
These calls are almost directly map into some of the primitives,
Dirty 有点难做到，
turns out that you know dirty, actually a little bit harder to do,
没有直接对应的原语或系统调用，
you know there's not a direct primitive for or system call for,
尽管你可以用一些技巧来完成它。
although you can sort of more or less get it done with some tricks.
稍后我会稍微谈一下 Map2 ，
And I'll talk a little bit later about Map2,
也有办法做到这个，
there's also a way to do it,
但是并不完全是
but it's not completely
一种直接对应 Map2 的系统调用，
you know sort of a system call just directly maps onto Map2,
如果你有多个 mmap ，
it turns out that if you with multiple mmaps,
你也可以实现这个特定功能。
you can actually achieve this particular functionality too.
好吧？
Okay?
所以，思考这篇论文的一种方式是，
So one way to think about this paper is
内核开发人员可能并不完全受这篇文章的驱动，
the kernel developers you know maybe not totally driven by this paper,
但是内核开发人员已经扩展了这些，
but kernel developers, you know have extended you know these,
已经提供了这些原语，
where have provided these primitives
对今天的用户应用程序。
actually to you know today's user applications.
好的，我想说一下关于实现的事情，
Okay, I want to say a few words about the implementation,
只是更多的概述，
just a much more sketch level,
然后讨论一下应用程序本身，
and then talk a little bit about you know the applications themselves
看看他们是如何使用这些原语的。
and see how they use these particular primitives.
好的，让我们来谈谈两个有趣的方面。
Okay, so, let's talk about there's two aspects that are sort of interesting.
一个是发生了什么，
One is actually what actually happens
在虚拟内存系统中，来支持这一点。
inside the virtual memory system to actually support this.
我只想把它概述出来，
I'm just going to sketch this out,
比如最重要的部分是什么，
like what the most important pieces are,
事实上，
and in fact you know
这与即将到来的 mmap 实验有点相关，
this is sort of a little bit relevant to mmap lab that is coming up,
因为你要做类似的事情。
because you're going to do something similar.
所以今天的 Unix 的地址空间，
So address space typically in Unix today
是由硬件页表来表示的，
is represented by you know of course the hardware page table,
其中包含转换，
which contains the translations,
但通常它是用一组操作系统数据结构扩充的，
but typically it's augmented with a set of OS data structure,
与任何特定的硬件设计无关，
not related to any specific hardware design,
这些称为虚拟内存区，
these are called virtual, virtual memory areas,
简称为 VMA 。
in short VMAs.
基本上， VMA 代表的是
Basically, what VMA, what VMA represents is
记录一些关于连续地址范围的信息。
you know record some information about the contiguous range of addresses.
所以如果你考虑地址空间，
So if you think about an address space,
可能在地址空间中具有多个区段，
it might have a number of sections in the address space,
每个连续的范围，
you know each one contiguous range,
每个部分都是 VMA 。
basically for each section that would be VMA.
VMA 可能具有所有相同的权限，
And the VMA you know may also has all the same permissions
那个范围的所有页面有相同的权限，
through all the pages in that range at the same permissions,
它们背后都是同一个对象。
and they're backed by the same object.
比如，如果你有 mmap 文件
For example, if you have a mmap map map, mmap file,
然后，文件的 VMA 描述该文件的任何权限，
then, the be VMA for that file that describes whatever permissions for the file
同文件本身的信息一样，
as well as you know the information about the file itself,
比如，与 VMA 在一起的文件描述符，
the file descriptor, for example, that goes along with that particular VMA
而且文件中的偏移量也是 VMA 对应的。
and you know the offset in the file were that VMA corresponds to.
事实上，即将到来的实验里，
In fact you know in the lab upcoming lab,
你将实现一个非常简单的 VMA 版本，
you know you will implement a very simple version of VMA
并使用它来实现对于文件的 mmap 系统调用，
and use that to actually implement mmap system call for files,
你可以在 VMA 中记录，
where basically you can record in the VMA,
文件描述符和偏移量，
you are literally the file descriptor and the offset
对应特定的 mmap 调用，已经映射的范围。
that corresponds to that particular mmap call, the range have been mapped.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
好的，那么第二个重要的部分，
Okay, so then the second piece you know sort of important
我们有一点经验，
and then we have a little bit of experience with,
这可能是值得的经历的是，
it's probably worthwhile you know going through is
Trap 或 sigaction 处理程序是如何，
actually how trap or sigaction actually the handler,
实际的 Trap 是如何工作的。
how an actual Trap will work.
实际上，你需要更小心。
Actually, you'll be more careful.
所以我们实现了一个用户级别的 trap ，
So we have a user level traps are implemented,
这是非常符合，
and this follows very, it follows very much
与 sigalarm 系统调用的大纲是一样的，
you know the same outline as actually the sigalarm system call
然后，当时钟周期到达时，
and then the up call that happened when a clock tick,
已经[超过]了时间限制。
actually [passed] the time limit.
所以这里的设置是
And so the sort of setting here is
不是时钟周期，而是页表，
not not you know clock ticks but page tables,
所以让我们假设有一些 PTE ，
so let's assume there's some PTE
标记为无效的，
that has that marked you know in invalid
或者它可能是只读的，
or maybe it's read only
而你在保存到其中，
and you're actually stored to it
那么，当应用程序访问这个 PTE 时，会发生什么，
and so what happens when the application accesses that PTE,
实际上是无效的，
that actually is basically invalid
或者没有产生有效的转换。
or doesn't result in a valid translation.
正如我们所知，
Well as we know,
CPU 跳转到内核模式，
then the CPU jumps into kernel mode,
跳入内核的固定地址，
jumps into the kernel at a fixed address,
想想 trampoline 代码，
you know you know look at the think the trampoline code,
内核保存状态，
the kernel save state,
比如保存到 trapframe ，
so, for example save to trapframe,
然后访问虚拟内存系统，
then basically asks you know the VM system,
现在做什么。
and what now, what to do.
虚拟内存系统可能会温和地执行某些操作，
And the VM system might do something so gently
如果这种情况发生在懒分配实验，
and in case if this happened in the lazy lab
以及写入时复制实验，
and in the copy-on-write lab,
你的 trap 处理程序代码，
where you know your trap handler code,
查看页表数据结构，
you know sort of looks at the page table data structures,
在这种情况下，将查看 VMA ，
in this case, resume will look at the VMAs,
查看范围是什么，
and you know see what the scope is
进程[折叠]的地址，
just to address that were where the process [folded] on
看看需要做些什么，
and see what needs to be done,
比如，如果它是 segfault ，
and so for example if it is a segfault
并且应用程序已经安装了处理程序来处理它，
and application has installed handler to deal with it,
那么向上调用，
then basically that up call
或事件处理程序将传播到用户空间。
or a handler of the event would be propagated to user space.
所以，我们假设安装了一个处理程序，
And so basically let's say there was a handler installed,
然后我们就可以向上调用进入用户空间，
then basically we're gonna get up call to into user space,
像 sigalarm 实验的方法一样，
in the same way as in the sigalarm lab,
它将在用户空间中运行处理程序，
you know that will run you know the handler in user space,
这个处理程序可能会调用 mprotect 来改变保护位。
the handler you know might call you know mprotect you know to change the protections.
然后处理程序返回，
And, then the handler returns to,
用户处理程序返回内核代码，
user handler returns to kernel code,
到达内核，
to kernel,
然后内核恢复被打断的程序。
and then the kernel basically resumes you know the interrupted process.
好的，而且你必须，
Okay, and you have to,
如果，当内核恢复中断进程时，
if the, when the kernel resumes that interrupt the process,
比如，如果处理程序修复了用户程序的地址空间，
you know if for example the handler fixed up sort of the address space of the user program,
那么指令可能会正确地执行，
then they might actually instruction might use execute correctly
或者如果出现问题，
or if something is wrong,
可能会立即重新进入内核，
maybe trap back into the kernel right away again,
如果，
if you know the,
如果硬件仍然无法转换那个特定虚拟地址。
if the the hardware still can't translate that particular virtual address.
这能理解吗？
Does this make sense?
再说一遍， sigalarm 实验，
Maybe there's, remember again, the sigalarm lab
然后这个就很熟悉了。
and then this would be quite familiar.
是的，我有个问题。
Yeah, I have a question.
那一种，
What kind of,
我想，当我们允许用户运行
I think when we're allowing the user to actually run
在页面错误上的处理程序，
a handler code on a page fault,
难道没有额外的安全漏洞，
aren't there additional security vulnerabilities,
可能会导致这一点，
that could result as a part of this,
所以我想知道能不能谈谈这件事。
so I was wondering if it could speak to that.
是的，这是个好问题，
Yeah, it's a great question,
顺便说一句，
by the way,
能不能每个人都把摄像头打开，
can you like maybe everybody turn on their cameras too,
如果可能的话，
if possible,
如果你愿意这么做，
if you're comfortable doing that,
我会很感激。
I really appreciate it.
我想班上很多同学也会感激的。
I think many students in the class will appreciate it too.
是的，所以有一个安全问题，
Yeah, so there's a security issue,
第一，人们怎么看，
the first, what do people think,
这是否破坏了用户内核（隔离），
does this break user kernel
或者不同进程之间的隔离。
or you know the isolation between different processes.
另一种问法是， sigalarm 是否破破坏了隔离。
Another way asking the question did sigalarm break you know isolation.
它是没问题的，
Would it be okay,
因为处理程序的代码
because the, that that code that the handler
仍然可以访问相同的虚拟内存，
would still have access to the same virtual memory,
我的意思是，如果有不同的虚拟内存用于进程
I mean, if there are different virtual memories for the process
对于每个进程，
and for like for each of the processes,
那么处理程序不能查看其他进程的内存，
then that handler shouldn't be able to look into other process's memory,
这样就可以了。
that would be okay.
是的，当然，
Yeah, sure,
当我们向上调用时，
when we do the upcall correct,
我们向上调用安装了处理程序的特定用户空间，
we're up, make the upcall that specific user space that actually installed the handler,
所以处理程序在相同的上下文中运行，
so the handler basically runs in the same context,
运行相同的页表，
as runs with the same page table
与应用程序安装处理程序一样，
as the application that installed the handler
所以它唯一能做的就是影响应用程序，
and so the only thing it really can do is you know affect that application,
但是那是应用程序的问题，
but you know that's the application problem,
不会影响到任何其他的应用程序，
can't really affect anybody any other application,
因为它不能访问其他应用程序页表，
because it doesn't have any access to the other applications page tables,
或者可以强制切换到它们。
or can force switch into them.
所以这是好的，
So this turns out to be fine,
当然，如果处理程序没有返回或者做了什么坏事，
of course if the handler doesn't return or does something bad,
最终，内核可以杀死那个进程，
in the end, the kernel just kill, can always kill the process,
所以没有什么，
so nothing really,
唯一可能变坏的是
you know the only thing that can go bad is
这个过程会伤害到自己，
you know the process can hurt itself,
但它不会伤害任何其他进程。
but it can't hurt any other processes.
Amir ，这能理解吗？
Amir, does that make sense?
好的，谢谢。
Yes, thank you.
好的，现在我想举几个例子，
Okay, so now I want to go through a couple examples,
看看你可以如何使用它。
and so to see how you could use it.
我将从一个非常简单的例子开始，
And I'll start out with very simple example
让我们自己进入其中，
to get ourselves into it
然后我们会转移到垃圾收集器，
and then we'll move to the garbage collector,
因为很多人问关于垃圾收集器的问题，
because lots of people ask questions about the garbage collector,
所以，这是一个很好的用来深入研究。
so that seems like a good one to dive into.
好的，我想说的第一个例子是琐碎的想法，
Okay, the first example I want to talk about trivial idea,
实际上论文中甚至没有提到，
but you know in fact there's not even mentioned in the paper,
但这是一种很酷的方式
but it is a sort of a cool way
来说明应用程序获得的能力，
of illustrating you know the power that applications get,
如果它们有这些原语可用的话。
if they actually have these primitives available to them.
基本的想法是建立一个巨大的记忆表，
And the basic idea is to actually build a huge you know memorization table,
而记忆表所做的，
and the memorization table is basically what it does,
它记住一些计算的结果。
it just remember you know the result of some computation.
所以，比如你可以用下面的方式来思考，
And so, for example you can think about in the following way,
假设我们在这里有一张表，
let's say we're here's our table,
表从 0 开始到 n ，
and you know table start to get whatever zero to some n
表存储的是运行一些昂贵函数的结果，
and what the table stores is the result of running some expensive function,
对于参数 0 ，或者其他什么 f(n) 。
for that argument 0 or for whatever f(n).
所以如果你愿意，
So if you wanted to,
如果这张表是预计算的，
you know if this table were sort of pre computed,
它想要在时间的开始，
it wants in the beginning of time
然后你想查找，
and then you wanted to look up,
比如你想知道 f(i) 的值是多少，
like you wanted to know what value for f(i) was,
你要做的就是在表中查找，
well what you do is you just look up in the table,
在插槽 i 里，
you know in the slot i
你得到将要计算的 f(i) 的值。
and basically you get the the value that f(i) would have computed.
所以这可能会返回一个昂贵的计算，
And so this would return maybe an expensive computation,
也许 f 是非常昂贵的，
maybe f is very expensive,
转变为一个表查找，
into a basically table lookup,
这是一个很酷的技巧，
sort of a cool trick,
存储预计算的结果，
you know to basically store the results for pre computes
并存储昂贵计算的结果，
and store the results of an expensive computation,
如果相同的计算很多很多次，
and if that's the same computation is actually many many times,
然后提前计算每个，
then you know pre compute good ones,
你可能会有好处，只要需做一点事情。
you might be an advantage to small thing to do.
这样的设置，能理解吗？
Does that setup makes sense?
好的，那么问题是，
Okay, so then the issue,
是的，当然是那个表或挑战，
yeah you of course is that the table or the challenge,
那个表可能很大，
the table might be big,
可能实际上很大，
might be actually in fact very big,
它甚至可能比你的物理内存更大，
it might be bigger than maybe your physical memory,
但是拥有它还是很好的。
but it's still nice to have it.
所以解决方案，
So the solution,
你可以用来解决这个问题的一个解决方案是，
one solution you know that you could used to solve this problem is
使用论文中描述的虚拟内存原语。
to basically use the virtual memory primitives as described in the paper.
原语。
Primitives.
你要做的是，
And what you do is
首先你分配一个很大的范围，
you know first of all you allocate a huge range,
但是不要真正映射，
but don't really map,
不要分配与该范围相对应的任何物理内存，
you know don't actually allocate any physical memory corresponding to that range
[]使用部分地址空间，
[] use part of your address space,
然后假设我要使用地址空间的这一部分，
then say I'm going to use that part of my address space,
必须存储那张表。
you've got to store the table.
然后，在一个页面上，
And then, on a page,
在表中没有内容，
the, there's no content in the table,
有个地址范围，
there is address ranges exist,
所以如果你做一个表查找，
so if you do a table lookup,
比如 tb[i] ，
like table i,
那会导致页面错误。
you know that will result into a page fault.
所以这个方案出现在页面错误上，
And so this plan is on the page fault,
你计算所有的条目，
you know, you compute all the entries
或者所有的页面都覆盖了表中的条目，
or you know all the page basically covers a bunch of entries in the table,
如果我们到达其中之一，
if we reach one of them,
你计算函数 f(i) ，
you're basically you compute function f(i),
把它保存在插槽 tb[i] 中，
store it in the slot table i,
然后恢复应用程序，
and then basically resume you know the application right now,
那个，
the,
当然映射到物理页面，
of course the map the physical page,
所以会有页面错误，
you know so basically take the page fault,
你分配页面，
you allocate page,
并在那个页中保存，
and may store in that page,
作为 f(i) 的结果，对于页面中所有插槽。
as a result of f(i) for all the slots in the page.
它的优势是，
And the advantage of it is, correct,
有几个优势，
if you know a couple of advantages,
如果你重新计算 f(i) ，
if you have to ever compute f(i) again,
你要做的就是表查找，
you know you're going to actually do the table lookup
你不需要做任何昂贵的计算，
and you don't actually have to do any expensive computation,
只需要表查找，
just table lookup,
事实上，即使你查找表 i 加 1，
in fact, you know even if you do a table i plus 1,
在那个特定的页面上会有一堆条目，
like there's gonna be a bunch of entries in the in that particular page,
它们基本上都可以免费了，
they're all basically can now be free,
只是做表查找。
you know just table lookups.
当然，你一直这样做，
Of course, you keep doing this,
然后你将会消耗掉所有物理内存，
then you're going to consume all physical memory,
所以页面错误处理程序还必须抛出一些页面，
and so you know the page fault handler also has to throw out some pages,
如果内存快用完了，
if you're running out of memory,
所以如果有太多的内存在使用，
so you know if much memories in use, use,
释放其中一些页面。
free some of them, free some pages.
当然，然后你必须改变保护级别，
And of course then you have to change, change the protection level
确保将来会出现这些条目的页面错误。
to make sure that you're going to get in the future page fault for those entries.
所以你可能要调用 Prot1 或 ProtN ，
So you have to presumably call you know Prot1 or ProtN
以减少页面的可访问性，
to reduce the accessibility of the page
这是论文中的术语。
and the terminology of the paper.
这能理解吗，这是一种方案。
Does this make sense, that's sort of a plan.
好的。
Okay.
是的，你需要映射它，
Yeah, you would need to map it,
需要从操作系统请求
would need to request from the operating system
将其映射到特定地址，对吧，
to map it to a particular address, right,
因为它可以去任何地方。
because it can go anywhere, okay.
是的，我们会去任何地方，
Yeah we're going to be anywhere,
需要操作系统告诉它在哪里。
as long as you know the operation system tell where it actually is.
好的。
Okay.
或许说得更具体一点，
Maybe to make a little bit more concrete,
实际上，我实现了这个方案。
actually I have a little implementation of this plan.
我们可以看一下，
And we can just look at it
看看是什么，
and see what are,
你如何使用现有的 Unix 原语来做到这个。
you know, how do you actually do that using the existing you know Unix primitives.
让我。
Let me.
好的。
Okay.
大家能看到 Emacs 的缓冲区吗，
Can everybody see the Emacs buffer,
字体够大吗？
is the font large enough?
我想这就是答应了。
I assume that as a yes.
所以这是应用程序，
So here's the application,
让我到最下面。
let me go to the bottom.
所以这是 main ，
So here's main,
main 基本上是 setup_sqrt_region ，
main basically setup_sqrt_region,
基本上是分配地址空间，
basically allocates address space,
但并不真正分配属于它的物理页。
but doesn't really allocate the physical pages belonging to it.
然后它调用函数 test_sqrt_region ，
And then it calls this function test_sqrt_region
以随机顺序遍历该表，
to basically go through that table in a random order,
检查表中该位置的平方根条目，
and you know basically checks whether the square root entry in the table for that position
是正确的平方根值，
is indeed the correct square root value
只需在之前逐字计算。
by just computing it literally before that.
好的？
Okay?
所以 test_sqrt_region 将运行，
So basically test_sqrt_region is going to run
它可能会产生页面错误，
and it's going to presumably generate page fault,
因为到目前为止还没有真正填满表。
because none of the tables actually filled in so far.
那么它是怎么，
So how does it,
我们怎么才能得到那些页面错误，
how do we get those page faults,
好的，这是一段代码，
well here's the sort of the fragment of code,
你需要安装一个处理程序，
that you need to basically install a handler
一个特定事件的信号处理程序，
a signal handler for a particular event,
我们在这里设置，
we were basically setting here,
安装 SIGSEGV 事件，处理程序 SIGSEGV ，
install for a SIG-, you know the SIGSEGV event, the handler SIGSEGV,
所以，当 segfault 发生时，
and so when a segfault happens,
当页面故障发生时，
when a page fault happens,
内核将调用 handle_sigsegv ，
basically the function, the kernel will call sig handle_sigsegv
你可以提取出故障地址，
and basically you can extract the faulting address,
这看起来和你的陷阱代码很像，
you know this looks very similar to your trap code,
你们以前见过很多次。
you've seen many many times before.
基本上，这个方案是非常直截的，
And basically the plan is very straightforward,
我们将页面映射到特定地址，
we map a page at that particular address,
因为那是我们想填入的地址，
you know because that's the address that we want to fill in,
我们必须，
we have to,
所以我这里的昂贵函数
so my expensive function here,
或者是昂贵函数的替换，
or the, the replacement for the expensive function
或者昂贵函数是平方根函数，
or the role of expensive function is the square root function,
所以我们要填入平方根的值，
and so we want to basically fill in you know the square root of whatever value,
它必须在表中的那个特定位置。
it has to be there at that particular location in the table.
所以，我们分配一个页面并将其映射到那里，
So we allocate a page and and map it there
然后我们计算该页的所有平方根条目，
and then we calculate for that page all the square root entries,
然后我们就完成了，
and then we're done
这个应用程序有点极端，
and this this application is a little bit extreme,
我所做的是，
what I did is
我在只分配一个物理页面的情况下运行这个表，
basically I run this table with only one physical page allocated,
所以不管最后一页是什么，
so whatever the last page was,
会通过 munmap 来释放它。
would just release it by munmap it.
所以我们有一张巨大的表，
And so we have a gigantic table,
用一个物理页面来表示它。
that's basically represented it by one physical page.
我们可以直接运行，
And we can just run,
我们想要，
you know we wanted to,
我们可以运行这个应用程序，
we could run this application,
会很激动人心，
it's gonna be that particular exciting,
为什么不呢。
why not.
所以，编译它，
So, compile it,
在一个表中随机地跳来跳去，
you know and basically go through and randomly bounces around in a table,
可能造成许多不同的页面错误，
presumably causing a lot of different page faults,
在所有条目中，
in all the entries you know actually work out
所以即使非常巨大，
and so even though there's gigantic,
这个虚拟平方跟表，
it square root page table, table, virtual square root table,
实际上，表的物理表示只由一个页面组成。
the actually physical representation of that table just consist of a single page.
这是一个非常简单的例子，
And this sort of example of one of the very simple example,
你可以做一件很酷的事情，
of one of the cool things you can do,
如果这些虚拟内存原语对用户应用程序可用。
if these virtual memory primitives available to user applications.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
您能不能快速地复习一下最后一点，
Could you just quickly go over that last point,
为什么只有一个物理页，
on why there's only one physical page,
我想我当时在想，
I guess I was thinking during it,
这听起来有点像懒分配，
like oh this sounds similar to lazy allocation,
为什么会不同，
why, why is it different
我想那回答了我的问题，
and I think that answered my question,
但是我不太明白，
but I I didn't quite follow,
为什么我们最终。
why we ended up.
好的，原因是，
Okay, the reason,
好的，所以当我们开始设置的时候，
okay, so when we start when we set it up,
我们没有页面，
we have no pages,
setup_sqrt_region 分配地址空间，
setup_sqrt_region actually allocates address space,
但是立即 unmap 地址关联的所有物理内存。
but then unmap all the physical memory associated with that address immediately.
所以，在启动点，
So the point of startup,
没有物理页分配给这个特定的表。
there's no physical pages allocated to this particular table.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
是的。
Yeah.
好的，然后我们遇到页面错误时，
Okay, then we get, when we get a page fault,
这意味着整个表中有一页，
that means there's like one page out of the whole table,
我们没有映射，
that we have not map,
我们没有映射页面，
we have map no pages,
但我们遇到页面错误，
but we're gonna page fault,
现在我们映射一个页面，
now we're gonna map one page,
在这一页里，
and in that one page,
我们要填上，
we're going to fill in
平方根 i ， i 加 1 ，或 i 加其他值，
whatever you know the square root of i, i plus one, i plus whatever,
只提供那一页。
just gonna afford that particular page.
然后，如果我们有一个页面映射，
And then, if we had a page map,
在这种情况下，第一次，我们没有，
which in this case, the first time around, we didn't,
就没什么可做的。
there's nothing to be done.
所以，现在应用程序运行，
So now the application runs,
在平方根表中查找更多条目页面，
you know and look up some more entries page in the square root table
可能会得到另一个页面错误，
and may get another page table for another page fault,
因为它查找的平方根条目，
because it was looking up a square root entry,
实际上不在分配的页面上。
that actually is not on the allocated page.
好的？
Okay?
所以在这一点上，我们得到了另一个页面错误，
So that point, we get another page fault,
然后我们分配第二个页面，
and then we allocate a second page,
我们对特定的页面计算平方根，
we calculate the square roots you know for that particular page,
然后我们 unmap 最后一页。
and then we unmap the last page.
当然，在实践中，你永远不会这样做，
These is of course like practice you would never do this,
在实践中，你可能会保留一组工作页面或类似的内容，
in practice you would try to keep a working set of set of pages or something like that,
但为了表明你可以走得相当极端，
but just to show that you can go pretty extreme,
你可以用一页内存来表示很大的表，
that you can represent like huge page, huge table with a single page of memory,
这个特定代码片段 unmap 最后一个页面，
this particular fragment of code unmaps that last one but last page,
然后它继续运行。
then it keeps running.
所以，在任何时间点，
So, any point instance, at any point of time,
只有一个物理页面在使用。
there's only one physical page being used.
这回答了你的问题吗？
Does that answer your question?
是的，我想是的，谢谢。
Yeah, I think so, thank you.
好的。
Okay good.
它就像，
It's just like, it's more like,
这显然不是你在实践中会做的事情，
this is clearly not something you would do in practice,
也许更多是可以让你知道原语的力量，
maybe there's more to show you know the power of the primitives,
你可以使用一个物理页面表示这个巨大的表。
you know that you can represent the gigantic table using one single physical page.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
好的，接下来我想做的是，
Okay, what I would like to do next then is
讨论一下另一个例子，
talk about another example,
特别我想讨论一下垃圾收集器，
and in particular I want to talk about the garbage collector,
因为很多问题都是关于垃圾收集器的。
you know since a lot of questions were about the garbage collector.
所以，垃圾收集器是一种方式，
And so you know yeah, so the garbage collectors are a way of
对于编程语言，
basically for programming languages
或者做内存分配和清除的语言，
or languages that basically do memory allocation and freeing
对于程序员的行为，
on behalf of the programmer,
所以程序员不需要调用，
so the programmer doesn't have to call,
必须 C 必须调用 malloc ，
like C correct you have to call malloc
然后必须显式调用 free 来释放内存，
and then you have to call free explicitly to free the memory,
使用垃圾收集器的语言，
languages that use garbage collectors,
应用程序只需要调用 malloc ，
basically the application only has, only basically call malloc,
再也不用担心释放内存的问题，
never has to worry about actually freeing the memory,
垃圾收集器将做这个工作，
basically the garbage collector will do the work
确定内存是否仍在使用，
to determine if the memory still is in use,
如果内存没有使用，
and if the memory is not in use,
那么它释放它。
then it's actually a free it.
所以这很好，
And so it's nice,
你知道哪些编程语言带有垃圾收集器？
you know what are some example programming languages that have garbage collectors?
Java 。
Java.
是的， java python Go 它们中的许多都是，
Yeah,java python, you know, Go, many of them actually correct,
几乎除了 C 和 Rust ，
almost you know other than maybe C Rust,
其他每种编程语言都有一个垃圾收集器，
there every other programming language basically has a garbage collector.
好的？
Okay?
所以正如你可以想象的，
So as you can imagine,
垃圾收集器有非常多的文献和设计空间，
there's a huge literature and a design space for garbage collectors
这篇论文的重点不是
and the point of this paper is not
尽可能使用最好的垃圾收集器，
like to use the best garbage collector possible,
但这里说明了，
but here you know basically illustrate
如果垃圾收集器可以利用
if garbage collectors could take advantage of
这些用户级别的内存原语。
you know these user level of the memory primitives.
所以，论文中讨论的特殊垃圾收集器是复制垃圾收集器。
And so the particular garbage colloctor the paper discusses is copying garbage collector.
基本方案是，
And the basical plan is sort of
顶层大纲如下所示，
you know the top level outline is as follows
有一个内存，
you know basically have a memory,
一个从内存中分配的堆，
a heap from which you know memory is allocated,
你将堆中的内存分成两部分，
you divide the memory the heap in two pieces,
一种是 from 部分，
one is the from piece,
也就是论文中所说的 from 空间，
what the paper calls the from space
另一个是 to 空间。
and the other is the to space.
假设我们开始使用应用程序，
And, let's say we're having started with applications to start
所有的内存都是空闲的，
and so all memory is free,
开始在 from 空间中分配内存，
basically start allocating memory in the from space,
假设我们分配了树状数据结构，
so let's say we allocated maybe tree like data structure,
你知道这是 root ，
you know that here's the root,
树可能有一个指向其他对象的指针，
so the tree and that maybe has a pointer to another object,
它可能有一个指向其他对象的指针，
and that maybe has a pointer to another object,
root 也指向它，
and that is also pointed to by the root,
像是带着一堆东西的环。
sort of just for a little cicle with of objects.
也许我们引入的应用程序也有很多其他的内存，
And maybe the application we introduced a lot of other memory too,
但已经没有任何东西指向它了，
but there's nothing pointing to it anymore
所以，唯一活的对象是这些，
and so basically the only objects live objects are the ones,
可以从 root 访问。
that actually are basically accessible from the root.
所以在某种程度上，
So at some point,
比如我可能已经分配了很多内存，
like maybe I've allocated lots of memory before
我们再分配一个对象，
and we allocate one more object,
结果就没有空间了，
and it turns out there's no space anymore,
应用程序要求再添加一个对象，
application ask for one more object,
结果发现已经没有空间了，
it turns out there's no space anymore for it,
因为整个 from 空间都被使用了。
because the whole from space basically has been used.
所以基本的想法是复制垃圾收集器，
So then the basic idea is in this a copying garbage collector
获取对象，
is to take the objects
并将其复制到用户的 to 空间，
and copy them over to the user to the to space
你这样做的方式是，
and the way you do it is
你从 root 开始，
you start from the root,
因为每个应用程序有一组寄存器，
because every application where every has a set of registers,
顶层指针保存的位置，
where basically this top level pointers are stored,
或者可能堆栈上有局部变量，
or maybe there's a local variables on the stack,
基本上有一组 root ，
basically there's a set of root
为了简单起见，我假设只有一个 root ，
and there for simplicity, I'm just going to assume there's one root
你从顶层开始追踪。
and you start tracing basically from the top level.
所以你把 root 对象复制到 to 空间，
So you know you copy the root object over to the to space,
这是你在这一点上唯一要做的事，
and you know and that's the only thing you do at that point
然后，当然，叶子指针，
and then you know of course that leaves you know the pointers
仍然指向它们以前的物体。
you know still pointing to whatever objects they were there before.
然后你想要把物体复制过来，
And then you're gonna want to copy the object over,
你检查，我们扫描物体，
you go and inspect, we scan the object,
当然，语言运行时确切地知道
then of course the language runtime knows exactly
对象是什么类型，
what type the object is
并且知道指向哪里，
and knows where the points are
查看那些指针，
and just look at these pointers
然后说，也许我应该多复制一些指针过来，
and says okay, maybe I should copy some more pointers over,
因为这些是线索，
because those are actually a clue,
是活动数据结构的一部分。
you know part of the live data structure.
所以我们可以选择顶层指针，
And so basically maybe we'll take the top level pointer,
查看那个对象，
look at that object,
复制那个对象到 to 空间，
you copy that object over you know to the to space,
更新这里的指针，
updates you know the pointer here,
用来表示它在这里，
you know to actually indicate that actually it has here
并将其指向对象的复制的版本。
and pointing it to you know copied version of the object.
然后，当然，
And then of course,
稍后我们需要记住，
later on we need to remember,
这个对象被复制了，
that we're actually this object has been copied,
所以你看到一些额外的信息，
so you saw a little bit of extra information
记住这些对象现在仍然在那里工作，
and remember that these objects are now still work there,
在这个过程中，
in this process,
将对象从 from 空间移动到 to 空间，
you know a sort of moving an object from the from space to the to space
并且在 from 空间中留下转发指针，称为转发。
and leaving a forwarding pointer in the from space, is called forwarding.
好的，所以我们现在，
Okay, so we now,
所以我们做了这个，
so we did this,
我们修好这个指针，
we did fix this pointer,
我们修好那个指针，
we fix that pointer,
还剩下一个，
there's one more left,
所以我们看看那个对象，
so we'll look at that object
然后像以前一样把它复制过来，
and we copy it over like before,
它仍然有一个指向这个对象的指针，
and it still has a pointer pointing to this object,
所以现在我们看一下这个特定的指针，
so now we look at that particular pointer,
查看指针，它已经被复制了，
look at pointer, say ah, that actually has already been copied
事实上，我们知道新的位置在哪里，
and in fact we know what the new location is,
所以，我们可以直接更新指向正确的位置。
so we can just straight updated to point to the right place.
好的，在这一点上，
Okay, and so at this point,
所有的指针都被正确地更新了，
you know all the pointers have been you know correctly updated,
整个结构，整个环，
you know the whole structure, you know the whole cycle,
对象从 from 空间移动到 to 空间，
basically of objects as we move from the from space to to space
所以，在这一点上，我们完成了。
and so at this point, we're done.
在这一点上，我们做完了，
At this point, we're done,
我们转发了所有的对象，
we forwarded all the objects
基本上 from 空间，
and basically the from space
所有在 from 空间的对象都被丢弃了，
now you know all the objects in the from space are being discarded,
现在是空闲空间了。
and it's now free space.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
这是复制垃圾收集器的基本方案。
That's the basic plan in a copying garbage collector.
好的，现在论文中使用的方案，
Okay, now the scheme that is used in the paper,
这里有几个复杂的东西，
there's a couple of sophistications,
我想谈谈它们。
I want to talk about them.
第一个复杂的东西，
First sophistication,
一种它们称为，
you know is that you know they actually they're called
被称为 Baker's 算法，
this is called Baker's algorithm,
这是一种老的算法，
it's an old algorithm,
其中一个很好的特性是，
and one of the nice you know features has
is
有时，它最初被称为实时的，
that sometimes it's originally called real-time,
real 的意思是它是一个增量垃圾收集器。
real what I meant is it's an incremental garbage collector.
所以，主要的想法是，
So, and the main idea is that,
这里我们有两个 from 空间和 to 空间，
here if we have our two from space and to space,
主要的想法是我们有 root ，
main idea is that you know we have our root again,
这是 root ，它有两个指针，
here's root, it had two pointers,
它指回来。
and it's pointing back.
主要的想法是，
The main idea is that,
它不需要停止整个世界，复制所有内容，
it's not really necessary to stop the world and copy everything over
然后基本上恢复[比赛]，
and then basically resume [competition],
唯一需要的是通过 root 进行复制，
the only thing really necessary is to actually move copy over the root,
基本上什么也不做，
and basically do nothing else,
在这一点上， root 已经被复制了，
and so basically you know at this point you know the root has been copied,
但是它的指针还指向这里，
but you know it's pointers are still pointing you know the here,
因为对象尚未被扫描，
because that object has not been scanned,
它的指针还没有更新。
it hasn't been, it's pointer haven't been updated yet.
它的基本思想是，
And and the basic idea is
每当应用程序调用 new 时，
then whenever the application calls new,
每次调用 new ，
you know whenever new call,
你扫描几个对象，
you scan a few more objects,
或者你多[转发]几个对象。
or you forward a couple more objects.
这是很好的，
And that's sort of nice, correct,
因为你分摊了
because basically you spread
复制整个活动堆的花费，
the cost of actually you know copying the complete you know active or live heap
从应用程序增量步骤中，
from the application incremental steps,
每个 new 调用分配一点，
every new every call allocates contributes a little bit,
来完成一个完整的复制操作。
you know to actually do a complete copy operation.
当然，应用程序也可能使用其中的一些指针，
And of course the application might also be using you know some of these pointers,
比如，如果 root 取消引用第二个红色指针，
for example if you know root will be dereferencing actually this, this second red pointer,
它还指向 from 空间，
it's still actually pointing into the from space,
当然，这是危险的，
and of course that is dangerous,
因为我们不应该跟踪 from 空间的指针。
because we shouldn't be tracking pointers in the from space.
这意味着每次取消引用时，
And so basically this means that every time you do dereference,
取消引用一个指针，
do dereference a pointer,
你需要检查，
you need to check,
检查它是不是在 from 空间，
check if it's in the from space, if in from space,
如果是这样的话，要做转发。
and if so, you know do the forwarding.
所以应用程序允许使用指针，
And so the application is allowed to use the pointers,
但必须运行，
but basically to run,
编译器必须对应用程序进行检测，
the compiler has to instrument the application
检查每个指针访问，
that basically every pointer accesses surrounded by that check,
所以，我们保持了不变量，
so that you know, we basically maintain the invariant that all,
在 to 空间中的任何指针处，
at any pointer in the to space,
指向 to 空间中的对象。
you know points to objects in to space.
我们需要确保，
And we need to ensure that, correct,
因为当我们最后完成时，
because when in the end we're done,
我们想把删除 from 空间，
you know we want to remove the from space
这样我们就可以丢弃它，将其作为自由空间重新使用。
and have, so that we can discard it and reuse it as free space.
好的，有什么问题吗，这是基本的设置。
Okay, any questions about this, this is sort of the basic setup.
好的，所以，如果没有问题，
Okay, so, if there are no questions,
关于这个方案，论文中提到了两点，
in the paper makes two points you know about this scheme
第一个，这很烦人，或者不好，
and one is you know it's annoying or too bad
你每次都要取消引用，
you actually have to do this dereference at every time,
所以这意味着加载或存储指令，
so basically this means load or store instruction,
不是单个指令，而是一串指令，
instead of being single instruction actually has a bunch of instructions,
也就是分支指令，
namely branch instruction
可能调用一个函数来执行它，
and perhaps you know calling a function to actually do it forward,
所以这会增加应用程序的成本。
and so you know that increase the cost of the application.
第二件指出的事情是，
The second thing that actually points out is that
让垃圾收集器并行并不是那么容易，
it is not that easy to parallelize the garbage collector,
因为也许在一个很好的配置下，
because maybe in a nice setting,
比如，你在一台多核机器上运行，
it's like if you're running in a multi-core machine,
那里有很多空闲的 CPU ，
where you know have a lot of free CPUs,
我把收集器放在后台，
basically I [realize] that the collector you know just put in the backgrounds,
遍历对象图，
you know traverse the object graph,
在它执行的过程中，递量地复制东西。
and you know copy things incrementally over as it continues.
但是如果应用程序同时正在使用这个图，
But if the application at the same time you know is using the graph,
这个应用程序有风险，
there's a risk you know the application maybe,
这里有一个引用检查，
you know, there's one of the reference check,
其中一个检查开始复制对象，
one of these checks starts copying an object,
同时，收集器也在复制对象，
while at the same time, the collectors also copying the object
如果我们不小心，
and if we're not very carefully,
最终可能会把对象复制两次，
we may end up with the object copied twice
而指针没有指向正确的位置，
and that pointer you know not pointing in the right places,
你可以很容易地看到这里有一个竞态条件，
you can easily see correct there's a race condition,
可能的竞态条件。
possible of a possibility of race conditions.
所以论文描述了一个方案，
So the paper basically describes a scheme,
如果你有用户级别的原语，
it's like if you had you know the user level primitives,
那么你可以做一些不同的事情，
then actually you could do something different,
你可以使用一个很酷的技巧，
you could do a cool trick
你可以使用虚拟内存，
and you can actually use VM, you know virtual memory
来降低检查成本，
to basically reduce the cost of the check,
几乎可以免费获得并发性。
in almost get concurrency for free.
所以基本的想法如下，
And so the basic idea is as follows,
我们有相同的设置，
you know we have our same setup,
我们的 from 和 to 。
you know our from and here's our to.
我们要做的是，
And what we're gonna do is
我们有区域，
like we're gonna have we're gonna have we're gonna region,
我们把 to 空间虚拟地分开，
we actually divide the to space virtually
或者我们把 to 空间划分一个未扫描区域，
or literally we divide the to space in an area that is a unscanned.
让我说得更清楚一点，
Let me a little bit more clear,
我们有一个区域，这里是扫描的，
we have an area basically, here is scanned,
还有一个区域是未被扫描的。
and an area unsacnned.
最初整个区域都是未扫描的，
And initially basically you know the whole area is unscanned,
当开始的时候，
you know when you know start out,
你做了从 from 到 to 的翻转，
you know you make the flip from the from to the to space,
还没有扫描过任何东西，
nothing has been scanned yet,
因为现在还没有任何对象，
because there's no objects at the yet,
但是方案是以相同的方式开始的，
and so but basically scheme starts in the same way,
我们复制 root 对象，
we copy over the root object,
它曾经在这里，
it used to be there,
然后把它复制过来，
and copy it over,
有一些指针，
you know have some pointers,
这些指针仍然指向原来的，
you know basically these pointers point still back into the,
糟糕，
oops,
是的，这些指针会指向老的 from 空间，
yeah, and these pointers will point back into the old from space
就是这样，
and so that's it,
现在我们要做的是，
and now we're basically saying, and what we're gonna do is
对于未扫描的区域，也就是这一点，
for the unscanned area, which is this point [],
我们在没有权限的情况下映射它们，
we're going to basically map and map them with no permission,
映射 None 。
map none.
那么这意味着什么，
And so what does that mean,
这意味着，
well, that means that,
在第一次运行应用程序时，
the first time run the application,
在我们翻转之后，
you know after we did the flip,
垃圾收集器翻转之后，
the garbage collector it to flip,
应用程序第一次使用 root 指针，
the first time the application is use the root pointer,
它会出现页面错误，
it will get a page fault,
因为这一部分地址范围是未映射的。
because you know that part of the address range has actually unmapped.
所以想法是，在错误处理程序中，
So basically then the idea is in the fault handler,
扫描一页对象，
scan one page of objects,
并转发需要转发的。
and forward to what that need to be forwarded.
所以我们在这个特殊的设置中，
So basically you know we in this particular setting,
到目前为止，我们只复制了 root ，
where we're only copied over just the root so far,
我们要通过 root 复制，
you know we are going to copy over root,
我们可以扫描 root 指向的对象中的指针，
we can scan you know the pointers in the object to which the root is pointing,
在这种情况下，只有两个，
in this case there are only two of them,
我们把这两个对象复制到未扫描的空间，
we kind of copy over those two objects you know into the unscanned space,
或者让我在这里稍微画的不同一点，
or maybe let me drawing slightly different here,
让它看起来像我们已经复制了这两个指向的对象，
just make it look like we've got copy over those two objects that were pointing to
我们更新，
and basically we update you know the,
我们将这条扫描线从这里移动到那里，
you know we move this scan line you know from here to there,
所以这是扫描过的。
so this is you know scanned.
所以在我们扫描完这一页之后，
And so after we scan the page,
我们可以增加保护，
we can actually increase you know basically protect
或者你可以取消保护扫描页，
or basically unprotect,
您可以取消对页面的保护，取消对扫描页面的保护。
you can unprotect the page, unprotect the scan page.
好的?
Okay?
然后，
And you know the,
然后应用程序只能访问特定的对象，
and then the application you know can just you know access the particular object,
因为我们转换了对象内部的指针，
because we translated you know the pointer that's inside of the objects,
它对应用程序公开是安全的，
it's safe to expose it to the application,
应用程序可以遍历这些指针，
the application can traverse those pointers,
当然，这些指针仍然指向已扫描的对象，
of course those pointers are still pointing to objects that are having been scanned in,
我们会再次出现页面错误，
then we'll, we'll get a page fault again
然后我们再多扫描一点。
and then we scan a little bit more.
所以它的好处仍然是递增的，
So it basically has the benefits still incremental,
你仍然可以做一些工作，
you can still do a little bit of work,
每次，
you know every time,
我们每次执行 new 时，
we can also do it every time new,
我们可以分配一些，做一些工作，
we can actually allocate you know some do some work,
但它还有额外的好处，
but it has the additional benefit,
不再需要指针检查了，
there's no no pointer check anymore,
指针检查仍在那里，
the pointer check is still there,
但它是在硬件中完成的，
but it's done in hardware,
虚拟内存硬件我们完成了这项工作。
with the page, the VM hardware does it for us.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
有任何关于方案，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this, about this plan?
我有个问题，
I have a question,
在处理程序中，你说扫描一页对象，
so, in, in the handler you're saying that you scan one page of objects,
但你如何知道，
but how do you know that,
root 引用的对象将指向相同的，
the objects that the root has references to will be will fall into the same,
比如你如何知道真正需要转发的对象，
like how do you know that the objects that really need to be forwarded,
为了不违反放在同一页中的不变量。
in order to not violate the invariant will be in the same page.
你会，
You'll be,
好的，页面中有一些对象，
okay, there's some set of objects in the page,
一开始，
the starting,
好的，但是我们假设，
okay but let's say you know what the,
好的，在我们开始翻转这些空间的时候，
okay, at the beginning when we flip this spaces,
to 空间里什么都没有，
there's nothing in the to space,
我们能做的是，
what we could do is,
我们能做的正确的事是，
like what the right thing to do is
我只是试着复制一页，
just copy I just tried to just copy one page,
复制或转发一页，
but basically copy over or forward one page,
复制 n 个对象，
basically copy n objects over,
这样它们就填满了完整的一页。
so that they fill a complete page.
好的。
Right.
现在，我们有 n 个对象位于这一页上，都是未扫描的，
Now we have n objects sitting on that one page, all unscanned,
然后，在某个时刻，页面错误处理程序发生，
then, at some point a page fault handler happen
然后垃圾收集器，
and then you know the garbage collector,
收集器检查这一页上的每个对象，
you know collector go through each object on that one page
并查看它的指针，
and looks for its pointers,
对于每个指针，
and for each pointer,
它会复制这些对象
it will copies over those you know objects
到 to 空间的未扫描部分。
into the, into the unscan part of the to space.
所以，如果任何人或者应用程序使用其中之一，
And so that if you know anybody or if the application would use one of those,
对象将得到一个页面错误，
what objects will get a page fault
并且它们可以扫描那些，依此类推。
and they can scan those etc etc.
这回答了你的问题吗？
Does that answer the question?
是的。
Yeah.
好的。
Okay.
哦，抱歉，我也有个问题。
Oh, sorry, I also had a question.
是的，所以在你将 to 翻转为 from 之后。
Yeah, so after you do this do flip the to in the from.
好的。
Okay.
好的，你从 from 空间开始，
Okay, you, you start out in the from space,
把它翻转过来，
you flip it up, you flip to,
复制为 to 空间，
you copied over to the to space
然后你调用 from ，
and then you call the from,
一旦你完成了扫描，
once you're done with the complete with scanning,
你已经做好了 from 空间完全清空，
and you're done with the from space is completely clear,
你只要把名字翻过来，
just you flip the names,
并且开始使用 to 空间来进行分配，
and you start using the to space to actually do the allocations
直到它装满，然后你再翻转一次。
until it's full and then you flip again.
谢谢。
Thank you.
还有什么问题吗？
Any further questions?
所以，这篇论文还提出的一个论点是，
So one of the, one of the things that one of the arguments the paper also makes,
虚拟内存系统或使用虚拟内存的另一件事，
that you know the one other thing that the VM system or using VM,
简化了并发性，
simplifies is basically concurrency,
它的论点是，
the argument is that,
收集器只能浏览未扫描的页面，
basically the collector you can just go through the unscanned pages,
所以我们有浏览和扫描页面，
so we have go through and scan pages
每次扫描一个页面，
and basically scan one page at a time,
它保证应用程序没有指针，
and if it is guaranteed that the application has no pointers
或者不能在同一时间内访问那个页面，
or cannot access in the same time that page,
因为它是未映射的。
because its unmap.
所以，只需要，
And so, you know as long as the,
所以，页面硬件引入了
so the paging hardware basically sort of introduces
显式同步或竞态保护，
explicit synchronization or protection against races,
因为只有收集器在 from 能访问那个页面，
because only the collector can access that page at the from
应用程序实际上不能访问那个页面。
and the application can actually not access the page.
所以它提供了一个很好的自动并行性，
So it gives a nice automatic parallelism,
应用程序可以运行并执行它的工作，
where the application can run and do its business,
收集器可以做它的工作，
the collector can do its business,
并且它们永远不会踩到对方的脚趾，
and they will never step on each other's toes,
因为如果应用程序遇到未扫描的页面，
because if the application ever will touch an unscanned page
将获得一个页面错误，
and it get a page fault,
而且收集器从来不碰扫描过的页面，
and, and the collector never touches scanned pages,
所以永远不会干扰应用程序。
and so will never interfere with the application.
所以你可以免费得到并行，
So you get sort of concurrency for free,
但它实际上有一个棘手的问题。
but it actually has a tricky issue.
虽然几乎是免费的，
Although it's almost for free,
实际上有一件事你必须安排，
you know there's actually one thing you actually have to arrange,
就是区域，
which is the area, correct,
在未扫描区域，是未映射的，
in the unscanned area, which actually unmapped,
所以我们看一下前面的图片，
so we look at our picture from before,
这里有两个，
here are two,
这里是 from ，这里是 to ，
where here's our from, here's our to,
我们把它分成了未扫描的和已扫描的区域，
and you know we have split in the unscanned, scanned the area,
并且未扫描的，它的保护位是 None 。
and unscanned it has no, none, protect none.
所以这就提出了一个问题，
So that raises the question,
收集器是如何通过，
you know how this actually do collector go through,
因为我们不能访问这些页面，
because we can't actually access those pages,
因为它们是未映射的，是无法访问的。
because you know they're unmap, correct, they're inaccessible.
所以，技巧是这样的，
And so and the trick is basically as follows,
这就是 map2 的作用，
and this is where map2 comes in,
我们要做的是映射相同的物理内存，
what we're gonna do is actually going to map that same physical memory,
我们映射一次，
we mapped at once, correct,
我们这样映射一次，
we mapped at once in this way,
然后以收集器的角度再映射一次，
and gonna map the second time in the collector's view,
收集器视角的 to 空间。
sort of the collector's view of the to space.
所以，这里是收集器的角度，这里是应用的角度，
So here's collector's view, here's the app view
从收集器的角度来看，
and in the collector's view,
仍然有和以前一样 to 和 from 。
where I still have to and from exactly like before.
哎呀，让我试试。
Oops, let me try.
我们有 to 和 from 。
We have to and from.
我们实际上在做的是，
And what we're doing actually
这是我们的未扫描区域，
you know here's our unscanned area,
但在收集器看来，我们映射那些未扫描区域为可读写，
but in the collector, we map actually those unscanned area read and write,
这样收集器才能通过，
and so that the collector actually can go through,
扫描对象转发指针是必要的。
look at the, scan the objects you know and forward pointer is necessary.
所以这是需要 map2 调用的地方，
And so the here's look at the place where this map2 call is necessary,
排列物理内存映射两次，
where arrange physical piece of physical memory is actually mapped twice
在应用程序的地址空间中，
in the address space of an application,
以两种不同的保护级别，
at two different levels of protection,
让这样的场景是可行的。
to basically make things, scenario like this work.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
我有个问题，
I have a question,
你会给应用程序中的每个收集器
do you, do you kind of give each collector in the app,
不同版本的页表，还是。
different versions of the page table, or.
不，它们有相同的页表，
No, they have the same page table, correct,
但是它们把内存映射到两个地方，
but they have the memory mapped in two place,
物理内存映射在地址空间中的两个不同位置，
the physical memory map in two different places in the address space,
在页表中的两个不同位置。
in two different places places in page table.
而且，在一个地方，映射是无效的，
And, in one place you basically the mapping is invalid,
在另一个地址范围中，映射是可读写的。
and in the other address range, you make the mapping read write.
好的。
Okay.
我把这个说得更清楚一点，
Let me make, make a make this a little bit more clear,
因为很多关于它的问题。
since there were so many questions about it.
我有一个对这个想法的的简单实现，
I actually have a trivial implementation of actually this basic idea,
论文中描述的想法，
the idea that was described in the paper,
你可以了解得更具体一点。
that you could make it a little bit more concrete.
所以，让我来介绍一下，
And so, let me walk through this
请随意问问题，
and ask feel free to jump in,
基本上实现了论文中所描述的内容，
basically toy implementation of what's described in the paper
我敢肯定它有漏洞，
and I'm sure it has bugs,
我的意思是，我没有认真地测试过它，
I mean, I haven't really tested this in any way seriously,
但它主要描述了，
but it's mostly there's illustrates
让一切变得更具体。
you know to make everything slightly more concrete.
所以，收集器，
So the collector,
应用程序使用的 API 是，
the API if you will that the application uses is,
一个 new 和 readptr ，
a new and readptr,
readptr 检查指针是否在 from 空间中，
and readptr is that basically does the check whether pointers in from space,
如果它在 from 空间中，则需要复制，
and if it is in the from space, that needs to be copied
当然，当我们使用虚拟内存技巧时，
and of course when we're using VM tricks,
那么 readptr 将会非常轻，
then basically this readptr is going to be very cheap,
我们只返回参数。
we basically return the [] return the argument.
如果我们只针对这个简单的应用程序，
If we're just for this simple application,
我有一个链表，它有两个 root ，
I have a linked list and it has two roots,
指向，
you know pointing,
一个指向链表的头部，一个指向链表的最后一个节点，
one to the head and one to the last node of the linked list,
这是一个循环链表，
it's a circular linked list,
没有什么真正令人兴奋的事情发生，
and nothing really too exciting going on,
基本上应用程序所做的是，
basically what the application [] does is,
上千次创建列表，
you know thousand times makes the list
make_clist 和 check_clist ，
and make_clist and check_clist,
所以它会产生很多垃圾，
and so it generates a lot of garbage,
比如每次 make_clist 完成，
like everytime after to make_clist is done,
它会产生一个新的，
it's going to make a new one
所以上一个列表成了垃圾。
and so the last list is basically garbage.
所以收集器有事情要做，
And so the collector actually has something to do
make_clist 就是一些难看的代码，
and make_clist you know is basically a little bit of ugly code,
主要是因为每个指针都包裹在 readptr 中，
mostly because you know every pointer needs to be wrapped in this readptr check,
通常情况下，当然会由编译器生成，
normally, of course would be generated by a compiler
我没有针对垃圾收集语言的编译器，
and I don't really have a compiler for a garbage collected language
所以我只是在模拟可能由编译器生成的。
and so I'm just simulating what may be a compiler that might have generated.
基本上，代码所做的是，
And basically you want you know the code does is,
它构建的至少具有 LISTSZ 的列表，
it goes through the built a list of at least LISTSZ,
分配一个新元素，
allocates a new element
放到列表的开头，
and stick to the prepend at the beginning of the list,
然后更新最后一个指针指向列表的开头，
and then updates the last pointer to point basically to the beginning of the list,
所以这是环形的。
so that's circular.
关于这一小段代码，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this little fragment of code?
所以最有趣的问题是，
So the most interesting question is,
收集器到底是怎么做的，
like what goes on exactly the collector,
让我们首先看看没有虚拟内存的情况，
let's first look at the case where there's no virtual memory,
我们不会使用这些技巧。
where we're not using these tricks.
所以我们只需要看看两个 API ，
And so we just have to look at two APIs,
一种是 new 和 readptr 。
one is new and readptr.
所以，这里是 new ，
So here's new,
忽略这个 mutex ，它是针对虚拟内存解决方案的，
forget the mutex, that is for the VM based solution,
基本上，
basically, I [] that,
我们假设我们有一段时间没有扫描，没有收集，
we're assuming that we're actually not scanning, we're not collecting for a while,
我们会检查是否还有足够的空间在空闲空间中，
were basically, we check if there's enough space left in the free space,
如果有足够的自由空间，
if there's enough free space left,
我们只是向上一点，
you know we just bump up to point a little bit,
分配对象并将其返回。
you know to allocate object and return it.
如果没有足够的空间，
And if there's not enough space less left,
那么我们必须翻转，
then we basically have to flip,
我们必须运行垃圾收集器。
we have to do the garbage collector run.
所以我们看看 flip ，
And so we look at flip,
flip 是切换 to 和 from 指针，
you know flip basically switches the to from pointers around,
转发应用程序包含的两个 root ，
and basically forward which you know the two roots that this application has,
从 from 空间到 to 空间，
you know to the from the from space to space,
所以让我们看看 forward 。
so let's look at forward.
所以这是 forward ，
So here's forward,
forward 查看 o 指向的对象，
it looks if the forward object that is pointed to by o,
它看起来总是在 from 空间中，
it looks always actually in the from space,
如果它在 from 空间中，
if it is in the from space
并且之前没有被复制过，
and it has not been copied before,
然后我们要复制它，
then we're gonna copy it
现在我们就完成了。
and now we're done.
所以我们把对象从 from 空间移到 to 空间，
So we moved the object from the from space to to space,
如果我们已经复制了它，
if we already copied it,
那么我们可以替换指针，
then basically we can replace the pointer,
我们有新的指针是，
you know we have the new pointer is
指向已经移动的对象的指针，
actually the pointer to the already moved object
并返回该指针。
and return that.
好的?
Okay?
所以这就是转发。
So that's forwarding.
所以，然后 readptr ，
And so, then the readptr you know we actually ever,
readptr 通过，
readptr to basically go through,
让我们看看 readptr 和垃圾收集器，
let's see what the readptr with the garbage collecter,
readptr 在这里，
just readptr it's like right here,
如果我们不使用虚拟内存，
if we're not using if we're not using VM,
它说做的，
basically what it does,
它做的是 forward 操作，
it does a forward operation,
在 forward 操作中检查是否在 from 空间中，
in the forward operation is checking if the from space,
如果不在 from 空间中，那就什么都不做，
if not in the from space, then, do nothing,
如果它在 from 空间中，则重新执行复制。
if it is in the from space, then do this copy again.
所以我们在这里看到这是昂贵的检查，
So here we see this sort of the expensive check,
检查对象是否真的在 from 空间中。
is really checking if the object actually sits in the from space.
有什么问题吗，
Any questions,
在我跳到使用虚拟内存技巧的版本之前。
before I jump into sort of the version that actually use the VM tricks.
好的，让我们来看看虚拟内存的技巧，
Okay, let's look at actually what the VM tricks,
所以设置在这里，
so the setup is a little bit, is here,
这里有一个名为 shm_open 的调用，
basically you know there's a call called shm_open
它允许你创建一个共享内存对象，
that allows you to create a shared memory object,
这是一个 Linux 调用或 Unix 调用，
it's a Linux call or Unix call,
它的行为几乎就像一个文件，但它不是，
and it almost behaves like a file, but it's not,
它的行为类似于文件，但它不是文件，
it behaves like a file, but it is not a file,
它只是驻留在内存中，
it just sits in memory,
没有与之相关的磁盘空间或任何东西，
there's no disk space associated with it or anything,
它就像内存中的文件系统。
it's like an in-memory file system, if you will.
基本上我们在做的是，
And, basically you know what we're doing is
我们分配一个共享存储器对象，
we allocate one of the shared memory objects,
我们将共享存储器对象截断为
we truncate the shared memory object to be
to 和 from 空间的大小之和，
the size of the sum of the to and the from space,
所以我们有一个空间，
so we have a space,
然后我们对于 mutator 映射一次，
and then we map it once in the for mutator,
并且对于收集器映射一次。
and we map it once you know for the collector.
所以这就是这里的操作顺序，
So this is basically you know the sort of sequence of operations here,
shm_open ftruncate 和两个 mmap ，
you know the shm_open, the ftruncate and the two mmaps
基本上等同于 map2 调用。
are basically sort of equivalent of the map2 calls.
所以我们看看，
And so we look at you know,
让我们回到我们的实现上来，
let's go back up to our implementation,
在虚拟内存情况下的 readptr 什么也不做，
the readptr in the VM case does nothing,
这里不会检查，直接返回指针。
you know there's no check whatsoever would return a pointer straight.
然后我们使用[]指针，
And then you know of course we used [] pointer,
我们会收到一个页面错误，
we're gonna get a page fault,
就像前面在平方根表应用程序中那样，
like as before in the square roots table application,
也许这里是页面错误处理程序，
maybe here's the page fault handler,
如果是一个页面在，
so it is, if it's a page on
让我在这里想一下，
and actually let me run a little bit here,
如果对象已经被移到了某个地方，并且位于未扫描的区域，
if you know the object was moved somewhere earlier and sitting in the unscanned area,
我们得到一个页面错误，
we're getting a page fault
那么扫描页面函数会运行。
and basically the scan page you know function runs.
但是扫描页面函数运行在，
and but you know the the scan page function runs
使用收集器的地址范围，
actually with you know the address ranges of the collector
所以它是可以工作的，
and so it actually can work,
因为 mutator ，应用程序不能触及这些页面，
because otherwise a mutator correct, the application cannot touch those pages,
因为这样我们就会得到页面错误。
because then we take a result in a page fault.
一旦我们扫描了所有的页面，
And once you know we can, you know once we've scanned all the pages,
那么你知道，
then you know the,
收集器使用户应用程序可以访问页面，
the collector actually makes the page actually accessible to the user application,
再看一遍 flip 可能会有帮助，
It may be helpful to look at flip again,
只是为了看看 flip 发生了什么，
just to see what happens, actually flip what happens,
我们切换， from 空间已经满了，
we switch from the from space is full,
我们将整个 to 空间标记为应用程序不可访问，
we make basically mark the whole to space as not accessible to the application,
然后我们移动，
and then we move to,
收集器将 root 头和 root 尾移动到 to 空间，
collector moves actually the root head and the root last you know to the to space,
应用程序不能访问或至少不能直接访问，
that the application cannot access or at least not directly,
将会导致，
and you know will result,
当应用程序访问 root 头和 root 尾，
whenever the application accesses root head, root last,
它会导致页面错误，
it will actually result in a page fault,
然后收集器可以复制东西，
and then the collector can copy things over
然后保护这个页面。
and then protect the one page.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，注意在处理程序中，
Okay note in the handler correct,
首先扫描页面是至关重要的，
it's actually crucial that first the pages scanned,
在应用程序可以访问的页面之前，
before you make you know the page accessible to the application,
因为如果你在扫描之前让它可以访问，
because if you were to make it accessible before you scan that,
如果有多个应用程序线程，
you know, and if there were multiple application threads,
那么那些应用程序可能会查看未扫描区域中的对象，
then those applications might be looking at objects on the in the unscanned area,
当然，我们需要禁止这样做，
of course that we need to forbid that,
这就是用来扫描的代码，
that's over this code basically for scans
然后提高保护级别，
and then raises the protection level,
以便应用程序可以访问这些页面。
so the application can access the pages.
关于收集器和使用虚拟内存的技巧，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about the collector and tricks to use virtual memory?
好的。
Okay.
在这种情况下，我想总结几点，
In that case I want to wrap up a couple points,
在结束之前，我想说明一点。
I wanna make one point basically before wrapping up.
一个问题是，
You know, one question to ask,
在这里你应该使用虚拟内存吗，
should you use the VM for this,
它做了那些技巧的回报，
it really is it does those tricks payoff
因为很多，
and because many of the,
比如许多其他的垃圾收集器，
for example garbage collectors and many garbage collectors out there,
根本没有虚拟内存，
that actually don't use virtual memory at all,
而是使用基本的设施，
but use basic instrument,
编译器实际上是
you know the compiler is actually
非常清楚生成的代码的设备，
very aware of the code generated an instrument you know the code correctly,
采用各种其他技巧会降低性能。
and as all kinds of other tricks to reduce the performance overhead.
所以观察结果是，在大多数情况下，
So the observation is that in most cases,
这是可以的，
it can be,
而且大多数情况下都可以通过额外的指令来实现。
and most cases could have been implemented with extra instructions.
也就是说，
And that is,
如果你是一个编译器或运行库，或者是一种编程语言，
you know if you were basically a compiler or runtime, or for a programming language,
或许那也不是那么糟糕，
then maybe that's not so bad,
因为编译器可以实现，
because the compiler can do the implementation,
但是如果你不是运行时应用程序，
but if you know there's not a runtime applications
不是编译器应用程序或编程语言设置，
not compiler application or a programming language settings,
那么可能会很痛苦。
then that might be painful.
所以事实证明，对于这些应用程序，
So it turns out that for some of these applications
根本不涉及编译器，
where there's no compiler involved at all,
比如，像检查点
for example like check pointing
或共享虚拟内存，
or you know do shared virtual memory,
那些确实需要这种原语。
those actually you know really needs these kind of primitives.
所以在实践中，
And so in practice,
是这种情况，
you know it is the case that
对于应用程序员，这些原始语不是值得的，
you know not application programmers I find these primitive worthwhile,
但今天的操作系统支持它们。
but basically today's operating systems support them.
好的?
Okay?
有人问，其实很多人都在问，
Some people ask, a lot of people actually asking,
发生了什么变化，
what has changed since,
自 91 年以来发生了什么变化。
what has changed since 91.
有一件事已经改变了，
You know, one thing that has changed,
当然，大多数 Unix 现在支持原语，
of course, like most Unix do support the primitives now,
实际上从 91 年开始有很多变化，
and in fact there are many changes since 91,
是的，也许很难想象，
yeah yeah, maybe hard to imagine,
但基本上虚拟内存系统在不断发展，
but basically there's a continuous development in the VM system,
所以如果你看 Linux 的 git 日志，
so if you look at like Linux you know git log,
你会发现它继续开发，
you'll see, you know there's a there's continued developing
内核的各个方面，
the all aspects of the kernel,
也包括虚拟内存系统的不断发展。
and including a continuous development of the VM system.
你知道一些更大的变化，
And you know some of the bigger changes,
在过去的十年里有什么大的变化，
what are some big changes in the last you know whatever ten years,
现在有五级页表，
there there's you know there's now five level page table
来处理非常大的的地址，
to deal with really large a bigger addresses,
有地址空间标识符来处理 TLB 刷新的成本。
there's address space identifiers to deal with TLB the cost of TLB flushes.
最近，大约在一年前，
More recently a year ago or something like that
称为 KPTI 内核页表隔离被引入，
something is called was introduced called KPTI kernel page table isolation,
这是因为 meltdown 攻击，
which you know is there because of the meltdown attacks
我们将在本学期晚些时候讨论。
and we'll talk about later in the semester.
所以，虚拟内存系统绝对不是静态系统，
So, you know the virtual memory system is absolutely not a static system,
几乎在任何内核的所有方面之后都不是静态的，
almost after no aspect of any kernel kernel is static,
几乎每隔几个月就会有大的变化，
there's a traumatic amount of changes almost every couple months,
在内核的不同方面，
in different aspects of the kernel,
所以，在系统中，有时会完全重写，
and so in systems, once in a while actually completely rewritten,
所以它总是在不断变化。
so it's always in flux.
好了，我说到这里就到此为止，
Okay, let me stop with that
任何人还有更多的问题，
and you know anybody has more questions,
请随时向提问，
you know please feel free to ask them
如果你要走，那就走吧。
or if you have to go, feel free to go.
我能问一下第一批幻灯片中的一张吗，
Could I ask about one of the first slides,
抱歉，我正在看，
where of, sorry, I'm trying to see it,
它是虚拟内存实现，这张幻灯片之后的两张幻灯片。
it's VM implementation like two slides after this one.
是的，就是那个。
Yes, that one.
你所说的地址连续范围是什么意思？
What do you mean exactly by continuous range for addresses?
哦，连续的虚拟地址范围，
Oh, yeah continuous range of virtual addresses,
VMA 复制 1000 到 2000 之间的范围，
so you know the may you know VMA copies range 1000 to 2000,
如果你有另一个地址范围，比如 2100 ，
and if you had another address range like 2100 or something like that,
那就有自己的 VMA ，
that would be has its own VMA,
所以每个 VMA 覆盖连续的地址范围，
so every VMA covers a continuous range of addresses,
上面没有洞。
there are no holes in it.
好的。
Okay.
这让事情变得容易了，
That makes it easier,
正如你会在 mmap 实验室中看到的，
as you will see in the, as you will see mmap lab,
这使我们更容易对事情进行处理，
that will make it much easier to reason about things,
VMA 范围内的地址没有空洞。
addresses in the range of VMA has no hole in it.
好的，那么这些是为了，
Okay, okay, so those are for,
这个特殊的情况， mmap 。
this particular use case, for mmap, right.
是的。
Yeah.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Okay,I see,thank you.
所以可以认为每次 mmap 调用，
So basically you can think about it for every mmap call,
就有一个 VMA ，如果 mmap 不重叠。
there's one VMA, if mmaps don't overlap.
哦，好的，我想我明白了，谢谢。
Oh, okay, okay I think I think I understand, thank you.
问一下对于高，
To ask, so for for the high,
垃圾收集器的 to 和 from ，
on the to and from like garbage collection,
什么时候停下来并重新开始，
when do you stop and start again,
我猜收集器可以一直运行，如果它是并发的。
like I guess collector runs can run all the time, if its concurrent.
是的，这就是虚拟内存解决方案最酷的地方之一，
Yeah, that's one of the cool things about this VM solution,
收集器可以一直运行，
the collector can run all the time,
一旦没有未扫描的物体，它就可以停止。
and it can stop once basically it has there's no more unscanned objects.
好的，所以你必须通过，
Okay, so you have, but you have to go through,
也就是说，
that means you,
所以你浏览所有内容，
so so you'll go through all of the stuff
比如 from 部分中的所有对象，
like all of the objects in the from section
你要做的就是把它们收集起来或者复制过来，
and all you're either gonna collect them or copy them over
你怎么知道你通过了所有的。
how do you know you've gone through all of them.
在某个时候，你追踪对象从上到下，
You, at some point, you you trace the object up and down, correct,
在某些时候，你不再添加任何对象，
and at some point, you're not adding any objects anymore,
因为你过去已经复制过了。
because you already copied them in the past.
好的，理解了。
Okay okay, that makes sense.
你不再增加，
You don't add any more,
因为你的未扫描区域没有增长，
basically your unscanned area is not growing,
所以，如果你的未扫描区域不再增长，你就不会。
so if your unscanned area is not growing anymore, you don't.
好的，然后当你把它复制，取消映射，
Okay, okay, and then when you copy it over you unmap it,
如果有人试图访问旧指针，将是无效的，对吧。
so if someone tries to access the old pointer is going to be invalid, right.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
Okay, that makes sense, thanks.
好的，回头见。
Alright, I'll see you guys later.
谢谢。
Thank you.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
好的，我想今天可能就到这里了。
Okay, I think that may be it for today.